[
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>In what <strong>five </strong>ways can the pre-colonial history of Nigeria be reconstructed?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The pre-history of Nigeria can be  restructured through:<br>\n    - oral traditions;<br>\n    - archeological findings;<br>\n    - study of serology;<br>\n    - the study of numismatic;<br>\n    - ethnography/anthropology;<br>\n    - the study of ethnobotany;<br>\n    - art forms;<br>\n    - written/documentary sources;<br>\n    - linguistics;<br>\n    - palaeography.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>a. List any <strong>three</strong> articles of trade exported to  North Africa from Western Sudan during the trans-Saharan trade.<br>\nb. Highlight any <strong>four</strong> factors that contributed to the  decline of the trans-Saharan trade.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)<br>\n    - Gold<br>\n    - Slaves<br>\n    - Hides and skin<br>\n    - Ostrich feathers<br>\n    - Gum<br>\n    - Kolanuts<br>\n    - Ivory<br>\n    - Beeswax<br>\n    - Camwood</p><p><br>\n(b)<br>\n    - The North African towns were embroiled  in internal and external conflicts.<br>\n    - The cities of Gao, Timbuctu/Timbuktu and  Janne declined in economic importance.<br>\n    - The Portuguese exploration of Africa  opened a new window of trade with Europeans on the coast of West Africa.<br>\n    - As the trade in gold was declining the  trade in slaves was increasing rapidly on the West African Coast.<br>\n    - The Europeans introduced items of trade which were cheaper and more attractive.<br>\n    - The Moroccan invasion of Songhai in the 16th century.<br>\n    - The power struggle in Bornu and Hausaland in the 17th and 18th Centuries.<br>\n    - Iron items were used for religious purposes.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Explain any <strong>five</strong> features of the economy of the Igala people in pre-colonial period.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - The Igala people practiced agriculture.<br>\n    - They were fishermen.<br>\n    - They practiced animal husbandry.<br>\n    - They engaged in internal and long distance trade.<br>\n    - They were canoe builders.<br>\n    - They were skilled in metal work.<br>\n    - Revenue was generated from traders and  conquered areas.<br>\n    - They were professional house builders.<br>\n    - They were hunters.<br>\n    - They were traditional health workers.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Highlight any <strong>five</strong> negative effects of the  trans-Atlantic slave trade on Nigeria.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - Christianity tried to put an end to  ethnic differences in the society by preaching the universal religion of brotherhood of man.<br>\n    - through the Christian Missions, western education was promoted.<br>\n    - promotion of legitimate trade.<br>\n    - some Nigerian languages were put into writing.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>a. Mention  any <strong>three </strong>city states of the Niger  Delta that had trade links with the Europeans.<br>\nb. Highlight any <strong>four </strong>roles played by King Jaja of Opobo in the commercial  activities of the Niger Delta.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)<br>\n    - Bonny<br>\n    - Nembe                                                 <br>\n    - Brass                                                   <br>\n    - Kalabari                                          <br>\n    - Buguma<br>\n    - Okrika<br>\n    - Koko<br>\n    - Old Calabar<br>\n    - Opobo</p><p><br>\n(b)<br>\n    - He led the Anna Pepple House to absorb many other trade houses.<br>\n    - He promoted palm oil trade after absorbing 14 out of 18 trade houses.<br>\n    - He effectively blocked the access of British merchants to the interior in order to ensure an  effective trade monopoly.<br>\n    - He continued to imposed taxes on the British traders in his domain even after the Berlin Conference.<br>\n    - His excellent connection with Igboland gave him direct access to the source and regular supply of palm oil.<br>\n    - His wealth and power enabled him to dictate the price of palm oil.<br>\n    - He shipped his palm oil directly to Britain.<br>\n    - Through his commercial activities, a new class of Merchant Princes emerged.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Highlight any <strong>five </strong>factors that contributed to the  decline of Benin Empire in the 19th century.<br>\n     </p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - Ascension of weak rulers to Benin throne.<br>\n    - The Benin Empire declined due to the loss of revenue as a result of the abolition of the slave trade.<br>\n    - The diversion of trade from Ughoton to Badagry.<br>\n    - Revolts by the vassal states.<br>\n    - Tributes from the vassal states declined.<br>\n    - Succession disputes within the Benin Dynasty.<br>\n    - The Yoruba Civil Wars made it difficult for Benin traders to transport their products by land to the port of Lagos.<br>\n    - The Fulani Jihad also contributed to the decline of Benin's economy.<br>\n    - Agriculture also declined.<br>\n    - British interference in the Benin affairs which led to the Benin massacre.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>a. List any three nationalists in Nigeria from 1922 to 1960.<br>\nb. State any four factors that led to the formation of nationalist movements in Nigeria.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)<br>\n    - Herbert Macaulay                             <br>\n    - Nnamdi Azikiwe                                 <br>\n    - Obafemi Awolowo                             <br>\n    - Abubakar Tafawa Balewa                 <br>\n    - Ahmadu Bello                                    <br>\n    - Sapara Williams                                  <br>\n    - John Payne Jackson                         <br>\n    - Samuel Ladoke Akintola                 <br>\n    - Adeniran Ogunsanya  <br>\n    - Mazi Mbonu Ojike<br>\n    - Micheal Opara<br>\n    - K. O. Mbadiwe     <br>\n    - H. O. Davies  <br>\n    - Anthony Enahoro<br>\n    - J. S. Tarka<br>\n    - Aminu Kano<br>\n    - Bode Thomas<br>\n    - Alvan Ikoku</p><p>(b)<br>\n    - The desire for self government.<br>\n    - Protest against European culture.<br>\n    - Discrimination against Nigerians in jobs, social life etc.<br>\n    - Experience of demobilized ex-service men after the World War II.<br>\n    - Exploitation of the economic resources.<br>\n    - Excessive taxation which was unpopular in Southern Nigeria.<br>\n    - Confiscation of African lands by the colonial government.<br>\n    - Deposition of traditional rulers.<br>\n    - High cost of living.<br>\n    - Repatriation of high company profit to Britain.<br>\n     - The role played by the press.<br>\n    - The role played by the political parties.<br>\n    - The influence of independence of former British colonies e.g. India, Pakistan and Ghana.<br>\n    - The effect of the proclamation of the Atlantic Charter.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>State any <strong>five </strong>reasons for the Amalgamation of Nigeria in 1914.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - The amalgamation of 1914 was done to harmonize the economy of the two protectorates.<br>\n    - It was also done to ensure a smooth colonial administration of the area.<br>\n    - It was geared towards harnessing the natural resources in the hinterland.<br>\n    - It was done to reduce the cost of administration by the British government.<br>\n    - It was done to solve the problem of inadequate number of British personnel in the  area.<br>\n    - It was to harmonize the administration of the Northern and Southern parts.<br>\n    - It was to ensure a firm grip on the administration of Nigeria.<br>\n      - It was to establish an outlet for the evacuation of goods and services from the  hinterland to the coast without any political obstacle.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Outline any <strong>five </strong>benefits Nigeria has enjoyed as a member of the United Nations Organization (UN/UNO).</p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - The United Nations Organization (UNO/UN) has provided Nigerians the forum to  discuss international issues affecting all countries. This has raised the image  of the country.<br>\n    - It has provided employment opportunities to Nigerians in the Secretariat and its agencies.<br>\n    - The Nigerian soldiers and police who have served in the UN peace keeping and peace enforcement operations have gained experience and financial benefits.<br>\n    - Financial support – Nigeria has received financial support to improve her economy through the IMF and World Bank.<br>\n    - In the field of Agriculture, Nigeria has received a lot of expert advice through its agencies such as F.A.O., World Food Programme etc.<br>\n    - Health and sanitation – Nigeria has also received a lot of support in the field of health – Drugs, immunization of children, HIV/AIDS etc through the World Health Organization and UNISEF.<br>\n    - Education – Nigeria has received educational aid in the form of books, science equipment,  computers etc.<br>\n    - Nigeria enjoyed global peace provided by the UN.<br>\n    - It gave moral support for the restoration of democracy or constitutional rule in  Nigeria.<br>\n    - The country has benefitted from the support given to the observance and enforcement of human rights.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "history",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Highlight any <strong>five </strong>reasons for the need to make the study of West African history compulsory in Nigerian schools.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p>    - It will help students to discover West Africa’s past.<br>\n    - It will help them to see the need to promote West African unity, harmony and  personality.<br>\n    - It will help create employment opportunities.<br>\n    - It will help them to discover their roots/heritage.<br>\n    - It will help them to acquire knowledge of the sources of West African history<br>\n    - They will be able to discover West African civilization.<br>\n    - It will also help them to develop tolerance among West Africans.<br>\n    - Students will be able to dispel the notion of white superiority.<br>\n    - It will help to promote patriotism among the students.<br>\n    - It will teach our students moral values.<br>\n    - They will be able to dispel the idea that West Africa had no history before the coming of Europeans.<br>\n    - It will help them to develop critical/analytical thinking.<br>\n    - It will serve as foundation for those who will pursue history at the higher level.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]